Amateurs vs. Professionals
Prev  |   |  Next

Amateurs vs. Professionals

"Amateur" used to mean someone who worked for the love of it. Such people often produce better results than those who do it only for money or even a lot of money

If you care enough about a task, invest the time to do it well. It should get quicker and easier and the results will be better and more "professional" in due time.

In the book The Three Musketeers, Dumas tells the story of how d’Artagnan who is a young swordsman without much of an official training, from a remote region of France, eventually becomes the best fighter in France. This is despite the fact that his peers, Athos, Porthos, and Aramis, have much more experience and training.

It may seem farfetched, but before the industrialisation of the Far East, and the way the West interpreted martial arts, with the coloured belts and all, there were regional masters of these arts, who practised them as much as they could and honed their skills. However, despite all that, they never ruled out that they would one day fight against someone who never fought before, and lose.

It took me more than a year to write The Enemy and How I Helped to Fight it which was my first real story, but it took me about two weeks to write Summerschool at the NSA. This is whereas the screenplay for the film Spaceballs (which was written previously by Mel Brooks, Ronny Graham, and Thomas Meehan) took "only" six months to write.

Similarly, it took Bob Dylan less than 20 minutes to write "Blowin' in the Wind" which is considered a masterpiece, but he likely wrote many lesser songs before that.

In 2022, amateurs (also known as "geeks") are often offered token pay, or even large salaries or one-off sums of money (while agreeing to do some commissions or jobs for free).

Prev  |   |  Next
Big minded ("Rosh gadol") vs. Small minded ("Rosh qatan")  | Home |  Hacking and Heroism vs. Conformism and Tragedy

Amateurs in Sports
Prev  |   |  Next

Amateurs in Sports

Before the industrialisation of the Far East, and the way the West interpreted martial arts, with the coloured belts and all, there were regional masters of these arts, who practised them as much as they could and honed their skills. However, despite all that, they never ruled out that they would one day fight against someone who never faught before, and lose.

In The Three Musketeers, Dumas tells the story of how d’Artagnan who is a young swordsman without much of an official training, from a remote region of France, eventually becomes the best fighter in France. This is despite the fact that his peers, Athos, Porthos, and Aramis, have much more experience and training.

The short-lived sitcom Phenom depicted a young skillful Tennis player whose happiness was ruined due to living in boarding school conditions. Even if she practised more, she lost the psychological war.

Building on the strategy for winning and amateurs we can see that in ~2022, most good paid sportsmen are increasingly enjoying their work, and don't mind losing too much.

Croatia were the runnerups of the 2018 FIFA world cup, despite being a small country.

8 First Place Winners in a USA National spelling bee

michael phelps record/

https://www.essentiallysports.com/atp-tennis-news-jannik-sinner-defeats-vasek-pospisil-to-create-history-in-open-era-tennis/

https://www.dailymail.co.uk/sport/football/article-4389760/USA-women-s-team-suffer-5-2-loss-FC-Dallas-U-15-boys.html

Prev  |   |  Next
Amateur-modelled commerce  | Home |  Christina Grimmie (1994 - 2016; RIP)

Big minded ("Rosh gadol") vs. Small minded ("Rosh qatan")
Prev  |   |  Next

Big minded ("Rosh gadol") vs. Small minded ("Rosh qatan")

The Israeli military was small and as there was a lot of work to do to properly secure the Israeli civilians it coined the terms Rosh gadol ("big minded") and Rosh qatan ("small minded") to encourage the soldiers to take initiative and try to perform their jobs as well as possible, regardless of the fact they were paid little.

This extends to non-military work, government work, and voluntary work or hobbies and endeavours: if you care about something, do it as well as possible and give it enough time as needed. It will get easier and faster in time.

For instance, a vendor on a candy store or an icecream parlour, should try to greet the customers, be friendly to them, offer recommendations to them if they ask, accept business cards with their personal web sites or social media presence and visit them, and generally treat every customer like royalty.

If you do this, you'll likely get more returning customers, bigger tips, bigger bonuses and raises, and you may be able to land a better job based on a warm recommendation from your superiors and coworkers.

The opposite is Micromanagement where you do exactly as you are told.

Note that the Nazis' Superior orders - "I was only following orders" is orthogonal to this. Despite common belief the Nazis were very big minded / "Rosh Gadol", which may explain their initial effectiveness.

One may opt to refuse orders completely, and given the bad reputation that Superior orders got recently, the "Off with his head" Shakespeare and Lewis Carroll parody of Absolutism is unlikely to happen anywhere. If the current Dutch heir apparent requests a private jet flight at nighttime for a non-Emergency (which is what foolishly killed Samantha Smith and her father, and six other people), she will probably be refused. She is unlikely to request that anyway but that is besides the point. [Why I picked the Dutch princess?]

If your superior in any way requests something reasonable, you should comply with their request and be bigminded about it. But feel free to refuse harmful orders or requests. Despite common belief, this should not cause anarchy, but rather bring peace and prosperity.

[Why I picked the Dutch princess?] I picked her simply because she is older than Queen Elizabeth II's oldest great-grandchild.

Prev  |   |  Next
"Live and let live; do and let do"  | Home |  Amateurs vs. Professionals

Chuck Norris
Prev  |   |  Next

Chuck Norris

Update about the factoids’ trend

My previous analysis of Chuck Norris and the Chuck Norris factoids trend turned out to not be the last word on the subject. It is well known that Norris took the facts to his advantage, and as a result became the most prominent actor in Hollywood (which I call "the Alpha Male"). However, shortly afterwards, the factoids seem to have fallen out of favour, and some time after that, Norris announced that he retired from acting.

Now, I still added factoids about other subjects to my collection. Then one day in 2019, I was chatting on the #gnu chat room on freenode and after giving someone some advice, I came up with a new factoid which I uttered there: “If Chuck Norris gives you some advice, and you do not follow it, he'll survive. However, you likely won't.”. To my surprise, my fellow to the conversation, told me it was funny. Some days later I spent some time with my sister's husband, who is an artist and a film maker, and showed him some of the software applications and web services, which I was familiar with as a Linux (or rather "GNU/Linux") user and developer. Then, just when he and my sister were going away, I told him I had some factoids on my site about Chuck Norris/etc., and he told me he was a big fan of those.

So what has happened?

What I think happened is that Norris started playing (and fighting) in roles he liked, even if he didn't get paid or got paid relatively little, or was paid after the fact. He became a happy amateur rather than an increasingly unhappy professional. I won't be surprised if he has agreed to appear at local schools' plays, and/or playing roles that were seemingly unlike his traditional Hollywood roles - just because he liked them.

As a result of that, I believe Chuck Norris, both himself and the fictionalised Chuck Norris Facts image, has become a new Hacker Monarch. Well Done!

Update about the factoids’ trend

To my knowledge, I was the first to have come up with factoids about a fictional female (= Xena the Warrior Princess). Later on, inspired by an IRC chat, I came up with factoids about a real life female, Summer Glau. These were followed by some factoids about Emma Watson, and more recently some about Taylor Swift.

My friends and I also came up with factoids about inanimate technologies and organisations such as those about Windows Update.

Prev  |   |  Next
Taylor Swift  | Home |  "Fear is the path to the dark side"

"Live and let live; do and let do"
Prev  |   |  Next

"Live and let live; do and let do"

While it had earlier occurrences, I derive this piece of wisdom from Saladin, a Muslim king and conqueror of Kurdish descent who is known for being one of the most effective warriors, and one of the most noble and merciful people in history.

During Saladin's time Palestine which is also known as "The Land of Israel" or "The Holy Land" was ruled and terrorised by Christian conquerors (e.g: the Knights Templar ). These were Christian fighters who originated from Europe, who were psychotic, psychopathological, vicious, sadistic, and vandals, who would have put the Nazis much less today's Al-Qaeda or ISIL to shame, and harmed the civilians in Palestine and were feared by them.

Saladin acquired a large army of loyal warriors, who all joined him by choice, had superior swords to those of the Christians, and lighter armour, and he set out to release Palestine from them fortress by fortress. But the most amazing thing is that he told the Christians something like that:

You can fight me or you can surrender. The choice is yours. Do what you want, you don't have to do what you think you must. If you choose to surrender, I will spare your life, disarm you and let you walk to Christian-controlled territory. If you choose to fight, I will try my best not to kill or harm you (but do note that protecting my troops is my priority), and then swear you not to fight me any more, and let you walk to Christian-controlled territory.

I trust you will make the right decision and entrust you with power. Whatever your choice will be, I'll accept it.

While some knights were probably killed, many of them survived and became happy, sane, and while ostensibly Christian, unwilling to fight Saladin. Even if their religious leaders told them to return, Saladin told them he is OK with the oath breaking and said he'll fight them again. This caused his opponents to fight extremely poorly, and be quickly disarmed. Following that, they learned their lesson, and would not fight Saladin again.

By letting people do what they want, they will likely do the best thing they can do. This is management by not managing and parenting by not parenting, which is and always was the best way.

Prev  |   |  Next
Epistemology: Truths, "Lies", A Dynamic Reality, etc.  | Home |  Big minded ("Rosh gadol") vs. Small minded ("Rosh qatan")

Criticism
Prev  |   |  Next

Criticism

Colour of the Bikeshed
Quote from "If—" by Rudyard Kipling

I feel that one should Encourage people to criticise them and try to get offended, because negative criticism highlights things where one can improve, including various falsehoods that one believes in, but are in fact false. (See: "All great truths begin as blasphemies"). On the other hand, if one only tries to hear flattery or yesmen, they are likely to get trapped in an echo chamber, and become surrounded by sycophants, and improve too little.

On the other hand, one should never try to please everyone because some people will always dislike some aspects of your work, and the best thing you can do is disagree and move on. Back when I referred a certain fellow open source developer (who is a Christian American) to my Star Trek: “We, the Living Dead” fan fic he objected to the use of the phrase “hot girls” there, and claimed I should delete the offending pages from my site. However, I refused because I didn't disapprove of using that phrase there, and even if I did, I'd rather not remove such offending material completely, but rather either revise it or add a disclaimer note.

Colour of the Bikeshed

A somewhat more involved case of criticism is Parkinson’s Law of Triviality or the "colour of the bikeshed" argument in which discussions about trivial matters which many people can understand are given disproportionate time. In this case it is important to sometimes avoid insisting on one's preference. Recently, the local Israeli Free and open-source software community contemplated whether to use WordPress or a static site generator for the new linux.org.il site and when the consensus settled on WordPress, I accepted that despite the fact that I preferred the other option. That is because wasting time on such trivialities will not be fruitful.

Quote from "If—" by Rudyard Kipling

"If—" by Rudyard Kipling is a famous poem which is the favourite of mine and many past and present people (including Ayn Rand). Quoting from it:

If you can keep your head when all about you

Are losing theirs and blaming it on you,

If you can trust yourself when all men doubt you,

But make allowance for their doubting too;

If you can wait and not be tired by waiting,

Or being lied about, don’t deal in lies,

Or being hated, don’t give way to hating,

And yet don’t look too good, nor talk too wise:

Prev  |   |  Next
Six kinds of fools: avoiding prejudice  | Home |  Do not be afraid to live

The legitimacy of Fanfic and Real Person Fic
Prev  |   |  Next

The legitimacy of Fanfic and Real Person Fic

I am an unapologetic and proud fan fiction and real person fiction (= "RPF") writer:

Why do you write mostly fan-fiction and crossovers?

Lawrence Lessig gives many good reasons for remixing in his book Remix: Making Art and Commerce Thrive in the Hybrid Economy which I have read and enjoyed. Writing fan-fiction and crossovers, whether in fiction or in non-fiction (see some of my crossover essays) is the writing equivalent of what he describes being primarily done with music and videos.

Our aversion towards fan fiction and an insistence on "originality" is mostly a 20th century fad, that is slowly (for some values of "slowly") diminishing.

Anyway, the various fiction franchises and idea systems that influenced me are a large part of me, and I cannot throw them away when writing my own works. I don’t have a lot of control of the ideas I come up with, but I know I must materialise them eventually.

https://www.shlomifish.org/meta/FAQ/#why_real_person_fiction

I feature or reference several celebrities in my stories (whether past or present) as a way of Real person fiction. According to the Wikipedia page, such fiction is likely to be legal if it is done in mostly good taste, which I believe and hope is the case for me.

The general consensus is that a celebrity generally allows himself or herself to be a subject of reuse in literature, and that includes me, Shlomi Fish.

Update (2 November 2019): I have now written a more comprehensive essay about why writing real person fan fiction is good.

Update (26 November 2019): I now realise that fan fiction and especially real person fiction can be used to help combat the flood of new characters and names that plagues many more "original" stories. People generally have a rough concept of what characters such as Chuck Norris, Emma Watson, Richard Stallman, Moses, or Miss Piggy, are like and generally can better remember them because they thought about them a lot.

Why I will continue to write my real person fan fiction (fanfic)

There has been a lot of fan fiction and real person fiction in the Hebrew Bible and among ancient Greek and Roman philosophers. For example, Plato's dialogues with his mentor, Socrates are clearly RPF. So were some of the stories that the Israelite nevi'im (mistranslated as "prophets") told about their contemporary or past men and women, whether positively - or often negatively.

If we look at present time, then the Muppets and Sesame Street franchises often invite real life guests as fictionalised versions of themselves to the show, to interact with the muppets. Parodies are also considered fan fiction and some parodies like Spaceballs or Last Action Hero (which also sports some real person fiction) are among my favourite films.

Moreover, fan fiction and especially real person fiction can be used to help combat the problem of the flood of new names and characters that plagues many stories that are more "original". People generally have a rough concept of what characters such as Chuck Norris, Emma Watson, Richard Stallman, Moses, or Miss Piggy, are like and generally can better remember them because they thought about them a lot.

Prev  |   |  Next
Selling for people stupider than you  | Home |  Do not interrupt foreign speakers for every mistake

"Fear is the path to the dark side"
Prev  |   |  Next

"Fear is the path to the dark side"

Master Yoda from Star Wars is a great hacker, despite being fictional, and we can learn a lot from what he said about being unnecessarily paranoid:

Fear is the path to the dark side. Fear leads to anger, anger leads to hate, hate leads to suffering. And I sense much fear in you.

When one is irrationally paranoid, he will become suspicious, distrustful, and overzealous, and demonise people who care about him, and cause him to lose property (including data) or even his life. As I noted in a tweet:

I'm a full professor at an ancient university and I got here through hard work, high intelligence (lots of very clever people think I'm very clever), persistence, pulling my weight and…

AMAZING AMOUNTS OF LUCK

I recall master Oogway saying “There are no accidents” in the first Kung Fu Panda film, which while using a very expected plot, was funny, fun and insightful. Not saying it's always the case, but many incidents happen to you because you wanted them or was prepared for them. Maybe luck has less to do with pure chance than we assume.

Thinking you have bad luck and being pessimstic may be self-fulfilling.

Following the Snowden findings, some people decided to go to great lengths to avoid the NSA, CIA, or FBI knowing about their private lives, and online services such as Google or Facebook "fingerprinting" them.

However, do you honestly think the NSA/etc. cares enough about you to harm you? In my #SummerNSA effort I have said many unkind things about an idolised version of the NSA, and nothing happened to me, my homesite, and my other online writings / blogging. (And I announced the "Summerschool at the NSA" informal screenplay on reddit some months before the Snowden findings of fact.)

Moreover, I had much earlier written and published The Enemy and How I Helped to Fight it, which is a surrealistic political satire that criticised the Hizbullah at the time, but I can also retrospectively tell had a lot of criticism directed at the IDF, Israel, and other organisations. Since my home address is common knowledge, Iran could have killed me a long time ago.

On freenode, a chat friend told me he was glad that Google has his gmail.com E-mail messages because it means someone else besides him has them, and they will likely not get lost like his previous E-mail messages got lost in a hard disk failure.

I keep most of my important digital data in public repositories on GitHub and other "code sharing" sites because to quote Linus Torvalds: “Only wimps use tape backup. Real men just upload their important stuff on FTP and let the rest of the world mirror it.”. Nowadays, one should use git as a version control system most of the time, but the point is that one should publish or perish.

(Note that there is also Google Drive and similar services, which are more friendly to laymen, have web interfaces, and have coarser grained revision history.)

My contact info is publicly available, and I actually wish for more people - of any sex/gender, ethnicity, talents and interests, race, nationality, etc. - to contact me and chat in any plausible medium.

This tweet reads: “I know many people that have lost priceless data forever because they decided that it needed the utmost protection. Family photos, months and years of coding work, a novel… all gone, because it *had* to be encrypted.”

Moreover as xkcd #538 notes, the bottleneck for revealing secrets is you and the amount of pain and intimidation you're willing to endure. When I was a teenager, a friend who was physically stronger, forced me to reveal the 4 digit password to my watch's secret phone numbers - not unlike the "Princess Bride" gate key meme. Moreover, as the xkcd hover text notes, if your data is worthwhile, then you'll share it far and wide.

I actually even hope my thoughts have been recorded and I wish to share them. I have had many good ideas for memes or franchises, and I'm not ashamed of my wrong, stupid and/or "dirty" thoughts. I recently publicly came out with my deepest secret which is (brace yourself) the fact that I'm attracted to physically strong and/or muscular women. And… turns out I am in good company, and I felt relieved.

So please do not be paranoid and overly possessive of your crown jewels.

Prev  |   |  Next
Chuck Norris  | Home |  Hakuna Matata - no worries and no problems

Six kinds of fools: avoiding prejudice
Prev  |   |  Next

Six kinds of fools: avoiding prejudice

There are two kinds of fools. One says, “This is old, and therefore good”. And one says, “This is new, and therefore better”.

— John Brunner, The Shockwave Rider

Two more kinds of fools. One says: “This is popular, and therefore good”. The other says: “This is good because it’s not popular”.

— Shlomi Fish (though may not be a 100% original sentiment).

(And recently people had prejudice against "mainstream" culture.)

It is important not to be prejudiced against things just because they are old, new, popular, unpopular, seem like "a religion", were hyped, seem blasphemous or cringeworthy, are politically incorrect, etc.

I've been criticised for still using XML and related technologies, because they seem to have fallen out of favour. But I have good reasons for using XML and use it for different use cases than JSON and YAML and various lightweight markup languages, which I also use and like for different purposes.

Similarly, back when the Friends TV show was airing, some hard core computer geeks dismissed it, due to it being too mainstream, while I found it very good. [friends-fan-fic]

Lately, some people have looked down on adult male fans of the show My Little Pony Friendship is Magic because it was originally intended for young children, especially young girls. This is even though most male adult fans (including me) are heterosexual and that they include some combat soldiers. In a tweet I wrote that “I've always considered myself a little "girly" and now I'm even kinda proud of it, and am an otherwise straight male. “You can never truly appreciate Gilmore Girls until you've watched it in the original Klingon!””. I think you'd be surprised at how much unmacho and geeky some of the best male warriors are.

[friends-fan-fic] I also wrote a friends fan fic episode that parodies the book The Fountainhead by Ayn Rand.

Prev  |   |  Next
People Can Change; Companies and countries and communities too  | Home |  Criticism

Great Hackers
Prev  |   |  Next

Great Hackers

The Fox in the Chickens Coop

A great hacker is an action hero that is aware enough of the essence of hacking to become a greater and greater hacker, despite whatever limitations he or she may have, and despite whatever setbacks they may run into.

Note that some great hackers were clearly fictional (e.g: Yoda, Darth Vader, Milady de-Winter, Miss Piggy, or even Fluttershy ), some were female (e.g: Sarah Bernhardt , Ayn Rand, and Taylor Swift) and some were underage (most notably Samantha Smith, Shirley Temple, and Macaulay Culkin ).

So don't let anything stop you.

Even our period's canonical "anti-geek", Penny from the popular sitcom The Big Bang Theory, is a wonderful great hacker. This is evident by her constant "hacks" (or "dispellings") of the rules and prejudice of the show's more stigmatic geeks.

[beauty-and-the-geek]

The Fox in the Chickens Coop

Despite common belief what happens when you put a great hacker (whether male or female) in a secluded place with many minor hackers or conformists, is not one crushed great hacker, but rather many great hackers, who spend time effort and conscious thought on satisfying their customers, peers and superiors. That is the "fox in a chickens' coop" motif as exemplified in the story of Joseph in prison in the Bible, and that of Milady de Winter in "The Three Musketeers", and in the film "Don Juan DeMarco" . In my "Summerschool at the NSA" screenplay, a fictionalised Summer Glau (the actress who is notable for being featured in xkcd: Venting ) is the fox (pardon the pun) who devours the hens of the fictionalised NSA.

I, Shlomi Fish, have done the same in real life in a top security Israeli psychiatric ward where I was hospitalised for being non normative, and for doing some foolish stuff. It worked surprisingly well, and I've used the collected wisdom of Moses→Saladin→Ayn Rand→the Beatles→Sesame Street→web 2.0 blogs and sites→My Little Pony / Taylor Swift and my own intuition and trial and error.

It took me about 6-to-8 weeks, and I suffered from the conditions of the hospital, but otherwise was able to hone my skills in benevolent psychological warfare, and also started writing some essays with my limited computing resources there.

[beauty-and-the-geek] It is wrong to look down on reality show contestants (and more recently - YouTubers) who, like older forms of entertainers / philosophers, are seeking recognition and fame. However, the show Beauty and the Geek was doomed to failure because not only are most attractive girls increasingly attracted to geeks, but they are increasingly quite geeky themselves.

As funny as the "Math is hard. Let's go shopping!" meme is, you can be a geek even if you are not too good at maths, and even shopping is a skill that can be honed.

Prev  |   |  Next
Hacking and Heroism vs. Conformism and Tragedy  | Home |  The Hacker Monarchs / Messiahs

The Hacker Monarchs / Messiahs
Prev  |   |  Next

The Hacker Monarchs / Messiahs

The nature of The Hacker Monarchs
Some notable hacker monarchs
Hacker Monarchs being Fallible
Other names for Hacker Monarchs

Traditionally in history, some great hackers have been motivated enough to change the world or improve it, and let no obstacle permanently stop them. They have become so powerful that they took over the direction of the world and together with some collaborators and supporters became sources of greatness. This is even though some of them were clearly or presumably fictional.

We'll call them the "Hacker Monarchs" ("Hacker Kings" / "Hacker Queens") which is a less loaded title than "Messiahs".

The nature of The Hacker Monarchs

We are still figuring out more and more guidelines for how a hacker monarch should behave, and likely there'll be future insights.

In the article about the Grand Nagus in Star Trek DS9, Quark is quoted as saying «Oh believe me, the Nagus has the greatest business mind in the entire Ferengi Alliance, always thinking ten, sometimes twenty steps ahead of everyone else.» and this is similar for a hacker monarch who is often ahead of the curve. A messiah also attempts to always think a few steps ahead.

A hacker monarch believes that the correct answer to the question "Who is the most powerful person on Earth?" is "I am". Furthermore, the only less powerful people are those who answer otherwise.

They also know they can improve themselves, improve the world at large, and enjoy themselves at the same time.

In addition, a hacker monarch wishes no man or woman to unnecessarily suffer or die prematurely and from unnatural causes. They also want every person and collective to improve and become better (= the Pygmalion effect as opposed to the Golem effect).

A hacker monarch is “their brothers’ keeper” to paraphrase on the Cain and Abel myth. For example Christina Grimmie has tried to adapt herself and her work to what she thought others wanted for several years before her assassination at age 22 (by a fan who killed himself later almost immediately). While it was ultimately her fault, she had many fans and viewers and friends who could have noticed (including I).

Some notable hacker monarchs

Some examples for notable Hacker Monarchs, from my Jewish/Secular Israeli and Western (Near East/Europe/North Americas) bias, are:

Moses

Cyrus the Great

Socrates

Plato

Aristotle (believed to have been a band of philosophers with a central poster boy figure)

Qoheleth / Ecclesiastes

( Jesus may have been a hacker monarch, but I have not studied his teachings closely, and have some natural aversion towards Christianity as an Israeli Jew. )

Muhammad

Saladin

Leonardo da Vinci

Galileo Galilei

Isaac Newton

Cardinal Richelieu

The American Revolutionaries

Alexandre Dumas (pere)

Jules Verne

Walt Disney

Ayn Rand

The Beatles

Sesame Street / Jim Henson / The Muppets

Samantha Smith

Richard Stallman / Larry Wall / Linus Torvalds and other Usenet / FOSS hackers with Eric S. Raymond writing the Magnus Opus CatB.

The fictional Jean-Luc Picard

The fictional Buffy Summers being the poster girl of "Web 1.0".

Joel Spolsky / Eric S. Raymond / Paul Graham (programmer) / Lawrence Lessig / Shlomi Fish and other software developers and bloggers / web writers of the ~2000-2014 web 2.0/"open content" revolution.

In Summerschool at the NSA, I believed Summer Glau and Xkcd will succeed me. While other "messiahs" / hacker-monarchs in the past tried to convince everyone else to consider themselves as such, it was only possible after the web became prevalent.

Following the Summer Glau "termination", it was believed that there now can be many simultaneous hacker monarchs, and that people can try to become ones while not dethroning (or sic transit gloria mundi) the previous hacker monarchs. “We don’t die. We multiply.”

Hacker Monarchs being Fallible

Note that even a hacker monarch may be fallible. Socrates almost got himself killed several times, and then he willingly drank the poison and died. Plato and Aristotle said equally blasphemous things, but learned from Socrates' fate and worked on better delivery so both died as highly revered and respected. The same story repeated itself during the Renaissance with Galileo and Isaac Newton.

Many Hacker Monarchs were two steps forward and one step back, like the fact Ayn Rand was anti-Open and anti-Amateur and confused selfishness with rational self growth.

Moreover, I still resent the fact that the characters in Buffy were competent, but on the other hand socially inept and lacked sexual assertiveness. This is a false dichotomy that I tried to rectify in my stories and screenplays where the characters are both competent and socially capable.

Having read The Three Musketeers, Dumas’ magnus opus, I recall feeling intimated by the competence and resourcefulness of Milady de Winter, until I eventually realised that despite being the antagonist, or because of that, she was the ultimate good in the book, and she became my epitome of sexiness in fiction. I disliked the fact that Dumas killed her so much, that I set out to carve different destinies for her in Selina Mandrake - The Slayer and for Faith (her rough equivalent in Buffy the Vampire Slayer) in Buffy - a Few Good Slayers.

So if you have a criticism against even the greatest hackers, voice it - we can only benefit from it. Also see The Emperor's New Clothes .

Other names for Hacker Monarchs

Hacker Kings / Hacker Queens ("Hacker Queen Regnent").

Warrior King / Warrior Queen / Warrior Queen Regnent / Warrior Monarch

King of Kings

"Princess of Princesses"

Best of the Best of the Best

In the Selinaverse they are referred to as "Q"s or later as "Sith"s.

A "Pope" by Principia Discordia.

Prev  |   |  Next
Great Hackers  | Home |  Make your own kind of music / Take your qualities to your advantage

Make your own kind of music / Take your qualities to your advantage
Prev  |   |  Next

Make your own kind of music / Take your qualities to your advantage

Similar to the Mama Cass Elliot song "make your own kind of music" or its Lady Gaga modernisation "Born This Way", I have given an interpretation of Captain Nemo (= "nobody" in Latin, and not to be confused with Nemo from the animated film Finding Nemo) in Jules Verne's novel 20,000 Leagues Under the Sea, whom people keep finding interesting for what he believes are superficial reasons. But these qualities are part of what makes us who we are.

The YouTuber band Cimorelli has used the fact that they are six sisters (who also have five male brothers) in a large Roman Catholic family, a trend which has received a lot of antagonism, from environmentalists, psychologists and the media, to their advantage, and as a gimmick. As a result, they published many videos of them covering hit songs, some original songs, and have been live performing and collaborating with other singers and entertainers.

Naturally, they are not the only YouTube success story. But if you get an opportunity, seize it. Were you invited to give a talk? Go for it. Even if you were invited from the "wrong" reason, you will pave the road for future lecturers. A sociology student invited you to talk to them about your work as an open source / open content creator? Go for it. You thought of a new Chuck Norris/etc. factoid? Write it down and share it on social media and chat. Someone asked you out and you like them and are single? Go for it. You have an idea for a nice video, story, screenplay, song, etc. Execute it.

I used to be jealous of Ayn Rand for writing so lucidly and coherently in The Fountainhead and in Atlas Shrugged, whereas my style of screenplays and stories was what I described as "staccato" where I do not mention any unnecessary details. However, Rand likely felt the same way about Dostoevsky and Tolstoy, whose overly verbose style is now the terror and hatred of many Literature students.

Similarly, current and future generations will likely appreciate my staccato style more than Ayn Rand’s. Make your own kind of music!

Prev  |   |  Next
The Hacker Monarchs / Messiahs  | Home |   Time >> Money

Managing Your Memory
Prev  |   |  Next

Managing Your Memory

As I wrote in Sherlock Holmes about Awk:

I enjoyed reading some of Sir Arthur Conan Doyle’s writings about the fictional detective Sherlock Holmes when I was younger, which were entertaining (although possibly distanced from the way actual crime investigation actually works), and interesting. I vividly recall one excerpt from the very first Sherlock Holmes story A Study in Scarlet:

His ignorance was as remarkable as his knowledge. Of contemporary literature, philosophy and politics he appeared to know next to nothing. Upon my quoting Thomas Carlyle, he enquired in the naivest way who he might be and what he had done. My surprise reached a climax, however, when I found incidentally that he was ignorant of the Copernican Theory and of the composition of the Solar System. That any civilized human being in this nineteenth century should not be aware that the earth travelled round the sun appeared to be to me such an extraordinary fact that I could hardly realize it.

"You appear to be astonished," he said, smiling at my expression of surprise. "Now that I do know it I shall do my best to forget it."

"To forget it!"

"You see," he explained, "I consider that a man's brain originally is like a little empty attic, and you have to stock it with such furniture as you choose. A fool takes in all the lumber of every sort that he comes across, so that the knowledge which might be useful to him gets crowded out, or at best is jumbled up with a lot of other things, so that he has a difficulty in laying his hands upon it. Now the skilful workman is very careful indeed as to what he takes into his brain attic. He will have nothing but the tools which may help him in doing his work, but of these he has a large assortment, and all in the most perfect order. It is a mistake to think that that little room has elastic walls and can distend to any extent. Depend upon it there comes a time when for every addition of knowledge you forget something that you knew before. It is of the highest importance, therefore, not to have useless facts elbowing out the useful ones."

"But the Solar System!" I protested.

"What the deuce is it to me?" he interrupted impatiently; "you say that we go round the sun. If we went round the moon it would not make a pennyworth of difference to me or to my work."

(Chapter 2 of A Study in Scarlet by Sir Arthur Conan Doyle, under the public domain in most countries.)

Conan Doyle was naturally exaggerating here in portraying the ideal of Sherlock Holmes (as few, if any, human beings can forget that the Earth revolves around the Sun), but the principle still stands: we need to make a conscious decision of how to manage our memory, because there is a limit to how many different aspects can put inside our resident memory, or otherwise we'll forget more important stuff.

So what does it has to do with the Awk programming language? Many decades after A Study in Scarlet, Eric S. Raymond had this to say in his book The Art of Unix Programming:

A case study of awk is included to point out that it is not a model for emulation; in fact, since 1990 it has largely fallen out of use. It has been superseded by new-school scripting languages—notably Perl, which was explicitly designed to be an awk killer. The reasons are worthy of examination, because they constitute a bit of a cautionary tale for minilanguage designers.

The awk language was originally designed to be a small, expressive special-purpose language for report generation. Unfortunately, it turns out to have been designed at a bad spot on the complexity-vs.-power curve. The action language is noncompact, but the pattern-driven framework it sits inside keeps it from being generally applicable — that's the worst of both worlds. And the new-school scripting languages can do anything awk can; their equivalent programs are usually just as readable, if not more so.

For a few years after the release of Perl in 1987, awk remained competitive simply because it had a smaller, faster implementation. But as the cost of compute cycles and memory dropped, the economic reasons for favoring a special-purpose language that was relatively thrifty with both lost their force. Programmers increasingly chose to do awklike things with Perl or (later) Python, rather than keep two different scripting languages in their heads.[90] By the year 2000 awk had become little more than a memory for most old-school Unix hackers, and not a particularly nostalgic one.

Falling costs have changed the tradeoffs in minilanguage design. Restricting your design's capabilities to buy compactness may still be a good idea, but doing so to economize on machine resources is a bad one. Machine resources get cheaper over time, but space in programmers' heads only gets more expensive. Modern minilanguages can either be general but noncompact, or specialized but very compact; specialized but noncompact simply won't compete.

(Emphasis mine.)

(Case Study: awk in minilanguages in The Art of Unix Programming by Eric Steven Raymond, text available under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonDerivatives licence, and hopefully quoted here (with attribution) under fair use auspices.)

I still keep awk out of my resident memory, but there are many other things I do not remember nor care enough to. For example, I do not remember the names of the current Israeli president or that of the current Israeli Chief of the General Staff. I am almost sure they are both great people, but remembering their names is pointless for me.

We have to manage our memory with care, or we'll forget stuff that is much more important.

Prev  |   |  Next
Forgiveness  | Home |  Selling for people stupider than you

What do "able" and "competent" imply?
Prev  |   |  Next

What do "able" and "competent" imply?

Sexiness as Competence

Karl Marx famously remarked

From each according to his ability, to each according to his needs

However, this is wrong because we should encourage people to be more able and more competent, and be less needy. So assuming we wish people to be more able, how do we measure it?

The first measure of ability is Money - the more money you have the more goods you can afford, the more you can give, donate, lend, or invest, and the more free time you have to do creative works.

The second measure of ability is Fame, the more people heard about you the more places will invite you to be present and even pay you for your time.

Fame has got a bad reputation lately, but I believe it is undeserved. Even if you are famous, you do not necessarily have to suffer from it.

The third measure is "luck" which is which opportunities you seize. The media went out of its way to present Paris Hilton, who was the canonical "alpha female" in the world throughout several years between 2000 and 2014, as incompetent, talentless, stupid, and lucky to have been a heiress by birth. However, despite that, she was the opposite of most of these. Moreover, if she utilised her initial state to her own advantage, then all the power to her.

Earlier in 1982, Samantha Smith may have been lucky for her letter to have arrived to the Soviet leader, but she hoped for that and planned that. It is likely that her friends found her a little "weird" for her habit of sending letters, given my friends looked down on a similar habit I had in the early 1990s before the prevalence of the Internet.

In today's Internet's social media, one can get a cheaper indication of some these, using views, upvotes, likes, "karma", reposts, replies, etc.

Naturally, abilities can refer to your various artistic, craftsmanship, sports, social, and intellectual skills.

Sexiness as Competence

Now here is something interesting: there is a strong correlation between how able you are and how sexually desirable you are to members-of-the-appropriate-sexes (MOTAS) (who may still be attracted to you whether or not you or they are in a relationship.).

Furthermore, fitness in biology in humans corresponds more to sexual attractiveness than to physical fitness. In the United Kingdom, the adjective "fit" has started to mean "sexy", "hot", "attractive" or "desirable" including such MOTAS who are not too athletic.

Some people may still think that sexual attractiveness is indicative of incompetence and bad form, but the opposite is true. Back when I referred a deaf friend of mine to the video Daily Gradvice (tongue-in-cheek sex/love/etc. advice by Grace Helbig) he complained that the quality of the subtitles there (which were generated by automatic Speech recognition) was like "her butt before she cleans it up". I took offence for that because I knew she was a wonderful lady and that was because she was so sexy and sexualised, not despite that.

[conclusion]

[conclusion] The end of the story is that I told my friend that I would try to prepare better subtitles which he and others would be able to use. While his original insulting delayed that, I eventually yielded functional subtitles for the video, which my deaf friend was able to use (and can be used by everyone else who wishes to use them).

Prev  |   |  Next
"One Tin Soldier" and the senselessness of destruction  | Home |  Taylor Swift

People Can Change; Companies and countries and communities too
Prev  |   |  Next

People Can Change; Companies and countries and communities too

It may surprise you, but people can change. Towards the end of my screenplay Selina Mandrake - The Slayer I describe such changes among traditionally stubborn men and societies:

Q, who had been revealed to be a humanoid, decided to appear less blasé and show some compassion for fellow organisms, including his ex-wives and children.

Kahless returns on The Day of The Living Dead to guide the Klingons back into rationality and carefulness instead of what became their traditional stubbornness and haste.

We admit to ourselves that sometimes amateurs (being people who like what they do, people who don’t play by the rules, and finally people who are not professional) can compete with the large budgets and high discipline of professionals, and even exceed it, because they can deliver more and at greater capacity, tend to think outside the box, and simply tend to avoid the many invisible rules that plague more professional structures.

Linus Torvalds surprised quite a few people by admitting that being rude was detrimental to the growth of the Linux kernel’s development community rather than something that he believed was good for it. There were some conspiracy theories about how exactly he came to that realisation, but it is not unthinkable for a person to change their mind.

Richard Stallman also decided to resign from his long term role as president of Free Software Foundation, which also was a surprise to many. The exact impetus for that decision is irrelevant, and Dr. Stallman is planning to remain active. Furthermore, the new president will likely be better and more effective than him.

Companies can change too. Under its new leadership, Microsoft has open sourced many projects, or developed them as open source to begin with. It also acquired GitHub, and despite some predictions of doom and gloom from paranoid users, it seems that the user experience (= "UX") of GitHub has improved since the acquisition.

Naturally, there are some paranoid "conspiracy theories" about evil Microsoft intentions to secretly take over and dominate the open source world. I on the other hand, try to avoid worrying ("Hakuna Matata") about such farfetched scenarios before they have materialised. I still recall some clueless users of Microsoft software saying that "Microsoft will buy Linux!" in the mid-to-late 1990s, and that naturally didn't happen because of the FOSS nature of the licences (whether copyleft or permissive), and the superior amateur-based model of development.

As the Chuck Norris factoid I came up with goes: “Chuck Norris' round house kicks are licensed under the public domain because no one else can successfully emulate them.”

Prev  |   |  Next
If the mountain won't come to Muhammad, then Muhammad must go to the mountain  | Home |  Six kinds of fools: avoiding prejudice

Taylor Swift
Prev  |   |  Next

Taylor Swift

We were discussing Apple's Swift language the other day on the #gnu chat room on freenode when I told someone there that he should charge 300 USD/hour for Swift projects because he disliked them so much. I also said the high fee may yield a higher demand. Then, since I had a browser window open with the most followed Twitter accounts and Taylor Swift was there, I noted she likely charges more than 300 USD/hour for her live shows. He told me that she shared her name with that language, and I noted that she should sue Apple for trademark violations of the supposed "Swift" trademark - and win. I joked that if "Apple sued Taylor Swift for violation of their Apple Swift language's trademark they will spend all their money in the bank on litigation and still lose.". Ha ha only serious.

I then realised that Ms. Swift has become a Hacker Queen by that time. While I think her face is good eye candy, she is not that beautiful in my opinion (but I think she looks much hotter with black hair than with her trademark blonde hair). Nevertheless, there are many things we can learn from her.

First of all is that she exemplifies the amateur model, because she does stuff for fun, rather than for money.

Her videos despite often being popular probably do not offset their production value in ads, but they are good publicity, provide fodder for remixes, parodies and covers, and are fun enough to produce so she can afford to offset the cost. She doesn't work for money or even for a shitload of money. She works for fun.

Moreover, Taylor is an unapologetic "attention whore" who often spends large amounts of money or even also time in activities that will make her look like a better person or more well known. Note that per Jeremiah chapter 9 22-23, “Thus says the Lord: Let not the wise man boast of his wisdom, nor the strong man boast of his strength, nor the rich man boast of his riches. But let him that boasts exult in this, that he understands and knows me, for I am the Lord Who practices kindness, justice and righteousness on the earth; for in these things I delight, says the Lord.” I not only hold it against her, but encourage other do-gooders to do the same. Furthermore, to paraphrase the film "For Love or Money" she doesn't do it because she seeks attention - she does it because she cares.

Otherwise, Taylor Swift is a great philanthropist who likely also donates to friendly individuals and realises that one should "cast your bread upon the waters" to quote the wonderful Biblical scroll of Ecclesiastes.

One advice I can give to Ms. Swift is to stop "speaking in riddles" which was also an issue of Terry Pratchett’s books and previously Ayn Rand's. I registered that idiom from the lyrics of a cover of Swift's song "Ours" (which I now much malign). I recommend she start writing a public snapshot of her personal philosophy ("Taytayism" or whatever) similar to my repository of this very document. It can be on GitHub or GitLab, or perhaps Google Docs.

Another piece of advice is to emulate YouTubers and start an "indie" YouTube channel, but this is not particularly specific to her.

Prev  |   |  Next
What do "able" and "competent" imply?  | Home |  Chuck Norris

YouTube
Prev  |   |  Next

YouTube

YouTube is a video sharing site which you've probably heard of. While there are many official videos by signed artists or by the film owners' copyrights, there is also a huge ecosystem of original "direct-to-YouTube" art created by the so called "YouTubers". They upload anything from bootleg videos of songs, to technical tutorials, to low cost covers (often just a man or a woman singing and playing a guitar, a piano or even an electric organ or A cappella), to parodies, to lyric videos, to live recordings of any musicians or comedians.

Now, some people still look down on YouTubers thinking that covers can never be better than the original, but having been introduced to the world of YouTube covers, I can often prove them wrong:

Tiffany Alvord’s cover of Hurt Me Tomorrow by K'NAAN

Jess Greenberg’s cover of "Highway to Hell" by AC/DC (somewhat NSFW - "boobs")

Alex Boye and Mom Bloggers United Africanised Cover of Katy Perry’s Roar

Christina Grimmie's (RIP) karaoke cover of Whitney Houston (also RIP)’s "I Will Always Love You"

Naturally, there is a lot of junk on YouTube - Sturgeon's law ("ninety percent of anything is crap") is still true, and that may include my own YouTube channel.

One problem with YouTube is that many videos have been removed, or censored, or disappeared, or blocked in certain regions (often by automated filters). Some people like me try to use youtube-dl or similar downloaders to download every video that we like from YouTube, and while some die hard copyright puritans have looked down on that, I still support that as a way to battle censorship. [Google vs. youtube-dl]

While I do not condone the recent YouTube shooting (by a woman no less), I believe that YouTube has brought it upon themselves by the aggressive and irrational content filtering and removal, that many YouTube creators and users have been witnessing.

I believe that signed artists and creators (or the somewhat more professional ones) should emulate YouTubers and start indie channels where they post regular collaborations with other YouTubers: from the better known to the relatively obscure.

[Google vs. youtube-dl] Someone told me in a chat, that he believed that Google (who owns YouTube) will do a DMCA takedown for GitHub to censor youtube-dl, but even if they were stupid enough to do that (which I doubt), it likely would not completely stop youtube-dl, whose open source public domain source code has thousands of git clones and forks.

Prev  |   |  Next
Strategy for Winning  | Home |  Amateur-modelled commerce